وَيَوْمَ يُنفَخُ فِي الصُّورِ فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ
And [warn of] the Day the Horn will be blown, and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified
فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ إِلَّا مَن شَاءَ اللَّهُ ۚ
and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified except whom Allah wills.
وَكُلٌّ أَتَوْهُ دَاخِرِينَ - 27:87
And all will come to Him humbled.
وَيَوْمَ يُنفَخُ فِي الصُّورِ فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ
And [warn of] the Day the Horn will be blown, and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified
فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ إِلَّا مَن شَاءَ اللَّهُ ۚ
and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified except whom Allah wills.
وَكُلٌّ أَتَوْهُ دَاخِرِينَ - 27:87
And all will come to Him humbled.
وَتَرَى الْجِبَالَ تَحْسَبُهَا جَامِدَةً وَهِيَ تَمُرُّ مَرَّ السَّحَابِ ۚ
And you see the mountains, thinking them rigid, while they will pass as the passing of clouds.
صُنْعَ اللَّهِ
[It is] the work of Allah,
وَتَرَى الْجِبَالَ تَحْسَبُهَا جَامِدَةً وَهِيَ تَمُرُّ مَرَّ السَّحَابِ ۚ صُنْعَ اللَّهِ
And you see the mountains, thinking them rigid, while they will pass as the passing of clouds. [It is] the work of Allah,
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم
I seek refuge in Allah from the cursed Satan
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
In the name of Allah, The All-Merciful, The Ever-Merciful
فَتَوَكَّلْ عَلَى اللَّهِ ۖ إِنَّكَ عَلَى الْحَقِّ الْمُبِينِ - 27:79
So rely upon Allah ; indeed, you are upon the clear truth.
إِنَّكَ لَا تُسْمِعُ الْمَوْتَىٰ وَلَا تُسْمِعُ الصُّمَّ الدُّعَاءَ إِذَا وَلَّوْا مُدْبِرِينَ - 27:80
Indeed, you will not make the dead hear, nor will you make the deaf hear the call when they have turned their backs retreating.
وَمَا أَنتَ بِهَادِي الْعُمْيِ عَن ضَلَالَتِهِمْ ۖ
And you cannot guide the blind away from their error.
إِن تُسْمِعُ إِلَّا مَن يُؤْمِنُ بِآيَاتِنَا فَهُم مُّسْلِمُونَ - 27:81
You will only make hear those who believe in Our verses so they are Muslims [submitting to Allah ].
وَإِذَا وَقَعَ الْقَوْلُ عَلَيْهِمْ أَخْرَجْنَا لَهُمْ دَابَّةً مِّنَ الْأَرْضِ تُكَلِّمُهُمْ
And when the word befalls them, We will bring forth for them a creature from the earth speaking to them,
أَخْرَجْنَا لَهُمْ دَابَّةً مِّنَ الْأَرْضِ تُكَلِّمُهُمْ أَنَّ النَّاسَ كَانُوا بِآيَاتِنَا لَا يُوقِنُونَ
We will bring forth for them a creature from the earth speaking to them, [saying] that the people were, of Our verses, not certain [in faith].
وَيَوْمَ نَحْشُرُ مِن كُلِّ أُمَّةٍ فَوْجًا مِّمَّن يُكَذِّبُ بِآيَاتِنَا فَهُمْ يُوزَعُونَ - 27:83
And [warn of] the Day when We will gather from every nation a company of those who deny Our signs, and they will be [driven] in rows
حَتَّىٰ إِذَا جَاءُوا قَالَ أَكَذَّبْتُم بِآيَاتِي
Until, when they arrive [at the place of Judgement], He will say, "Did you deny My signs ؟"
قَالَ أَكَذَّبْتُم بِآيَاتِي وَلَمْ تُحِيطُوا بِهَا عِلْمًا أَمَّاذَا كُنتُمْ تَعْمَلُونَ - 27:84
He will say, "Did you deny My signs while you encompassed them not in knowledge, or what [was it that] you were doing?"
وَوَقَعَ الْقَوْلُ عَلَيْهِم بِمَا ظَلَمُوا فَهُمْ لَا يَنطِقُونَ - 27:85
And the decree will befall them for the wrong they did, and they will not [be able to] speak.
أَلَمْ يَرَوْا أَنَّا جَعَلْنَا اللَّيْلَ لِيَسْكُنُوا فِيهِ وَالنَّهَارَ مُبْصِرًا ۚ
Do they not see that We made the night that they may rest therein and the day giving sight?
إِنَّ فِي ذَٰلِكَ لَآيَاتٍ لِّقَوْمٍ يُؤْمِنُونَ - 27:86
Indeed in that are signs for a people who believe.
وَيَوْمَ يُنفَخُ فِي الصُّورِ
And [warn of] the Day the Horn will be blown,
وَيَوْمَ يُنفَخُ فِي الصُّورِ فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ
And [warn of] the Day the Horn will be blown, and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified
فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ إِلَّا مَن شَاءَ اللَّهُ ۚ
and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified except whom Allah wills.
وَكُلٌّ أَتَوْهُ دَاخِرِينَ - 27:87
And all will come to Him humbled.
وَيَوْمَ يُنفَخُ فِي الصُّورِ فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ
And [warn of] the Day the Horn will be blown, and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified
فَفَزِعَ مَن فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ إِلَّا مَن شَاءَ اللَّهُ ۚ
and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will be terrified except whom Allah wills.
وَكُلٌّ أَتَوْهُ دَاخِرِينَ - 27:87
And all will come to Him humbled.
وَتَرَى الْجِبَالَ تَحْسَبُهَا جَامِدَةً وَهِيَ تَمُرُّ مَرَّ السَّحَابِ ۚ
And you see the mountains, thinking them rigid, while they will pass as the passing of clouds.
صُنْعَ اللَّهِ
[It is] the work of Allah,
وَتَرَى الْجِبَالَ تَحْسَبُهَا جَامِدَةً وَهِيَ تَمُرُّ مَرَّ السَّحَابِ ۚ صُنْعَ اللَّهِ
And you see the mountains, thinking them rigid, while they will pass as the passing of clouds. [It is] the work of Allah,
صُنْعَ اللَّهِ الَّذِي أَتْقَنَ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ ۚ إِنَّهُ خَبِيرٌ بِمَا تَفْعَلُونَ - 27:88
[It is] the work of Allah, who perfected all things. Indeed, He is Acquainted with that which you do.
مَن جَاءَ بِالْحَسَنَةِ فَلَهُ خَيْرٌ مِّنْهَا وَهُم مِّن فَزَعٍ يَوْمَئِذٍ آمِنُونَ - 27:89
Whoever comes [at Judgement] with a good deed will have better than it, and they, from the terror of that Day, will be safe.
وَمَن جَاءَ بِالسَّيِّئَةِ فَكُبَّتْ وُجُوهُهُمْ فِي النَّارِ هَلْ تُجْزَوْنَ إِلَّا مَا كُنتُمْ تَعْمَلُونَ
And whoever comes with an evil deed - their faces will be overturned into the Fire, [and it will be said], "Are you recompensed except for what you used to do?"
إِنَّمَا أُمِرْتُ أَنْ أَعْبُدَ رَبَّ هَٰذِهِ الْبَلْدَةِ الَّذِي حَرَّمَهَا وَلَهُ كُلُّ شَيْءٍ ۖ
[Say, O Muhammad], "I have only been commanded to worship the Lord of this city, who made it sacred and to whom [belongs] all things.
وَأُمِرْتُ أَنْ أَكُونَ مِنَ الْمُسْلِمِينَ - 27:91
And I am commanded to be of the Muslims [those who submit to Allah ]
وَأَنْ أَتْلُوَ الْقُرْآنَ ۖ
And to recite the Qur'an."
فَمَنِ اهْتَدَىٰ فَإِنَّمَا يَهْتَدِي لِنَفْسِهِ ۖ وَمَن ضَلَّ فَقُلْ إِنَّمَا أَنَا مِنَ الْمُنذِرِينَ
And whoever is guided is only guided for [the benefit of] himself; and whoever strays - say, "I am only [one] of the warners."
وَقُلِ الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ
And say, "[All] praise is [due] to Allah .
وَقُلِ الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ سَيُرِيكُمْ آيَاتِهِ فَتَعْرِفُونَهَا ۚ
And say, "[All] praise is [due] to Allah . He will show you His signs, and you will recognize them.
وَمَا رَبُّكَ بِغَافِلٍ عَمَّا تَعْمَلُونَ - 27:93
And your Lord is not unaware of what you do."